<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Observator vindicated, or An answer to Mr. Smythies's Reply to the Observator together with a brief, but just, censure on his sermon annex'd to it.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53185</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O123KA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825208</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825208</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29585</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53185)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29585)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2093:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Observator vindicated, or An answer to Mr. Smythies's Reply to the Observator together with a brief, but just, censure on his sermon annex'd to it.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Walter Davis in Amen-Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Observator = Sir Roger L'Estrange.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>L'Estrange, Roger, --  Sir, 1616-1704.</term>
               <term>Smythies, William, d. 1715. --  Reply to the Observator --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fredom of religion --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29585:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE OBSERVATOR VINDICATED, OR AN ANSWER TO Mr. <hi>SMYTHIES</hi>'s REPLY TO THE OBSERVATOR: Together with a brief, but juſt, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on his SERMON annex'd to it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Pudet haec opprobria nobis</l>
               <l>Et dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Davis</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29585:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29585:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER To Mr. <hi>Smythies</hi>'s Reply TO THE OBSERVATOR.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAVING lately ſeen a Pamphlet of yours, intituled a Reply to the <hi>Obſervator;</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with your Sermon annex'd to it, and finding by the Title-page thereof, that it had run through no leſs than three ſeveral impreſſions; I thought verily that there muſt be ſomething more than ordinary in it, in that it went down ſo well; and that <hi>that</hi> ſure muſt needs be a very choice diſh, which the Stationer had thus thrice
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29585:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſerv'd up in ſo ſhort a time. This whet my appetite to ſee what was in it, and made me greedily ſet my ſelf to the reading of it. But no ſooner had I gone through ſome few pages thereof, but I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently found it to be nothing elſe but <hi>Cramben ter coctam;</hi> a nauſeous publiſhing of <hi>that</hi> thrice, which no ingenious man wou'd have car'd once to have had a ſight of; and indeed had it faln onely into the hands of ſuch, it muſt have grown ſtale upon the Printers; who, inſtead of being at the trouble of a ſecond, and third impreſſion of it, muſt have been at ſome pains for the getting off the firſt.</p>
            <p>But the unthinking multitude are yours, and the Stationers beſt friends: for theſe ſwallow down any thing, juſt as men do Pills without either chewing or taſting them; and therefore as they have ſwallowed three impreſſions of your Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet already, ſo they may threeſcore more; and yet no man, that underſtands himſelf or what he reades, be inclined to think any thing the better either of you, or of what you write.</p>
            <p>But to let you ſee, how little you have advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tag'd either your cauſe or perſon, by expoſing your ſelf in print as you have done; I doubt not but to make it plainly appear to every impartial Reader (you your ſelf being one of them) that your Reply to the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> is ſo far from vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating you, in the matter charg'd againſt you, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29585:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>it confirms the charge, and more fully proves it on you. Thus when you are charg'd for breaking the Orders of the Church, in the matter of Sponſors, what is it that you ſay in your own Vindication? why, you tell us of a ſtory of your going to the Biſhop, to know <hi>his</hi> pleaſure about it; but what does all that tittle-tattle of your going to the Biſhop ſignifie? but onely to tell us plainly, that you did indeed break the Orders of the Church, but not without his Orders for it. This is the firſt time that I ever heard a Biſhop had power to give ſuch Orders: he may indeed, by virtue of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical obedience I owe him, order me to obſerve the Rules and Canons of the Church; but, by what power or authority he can appoint or permit the breach of them, I underſtand not. When therefore you went to the Biſhop, to conſult with <hi>him</hi> about this affair; you had been better advis'd, had you gone and conſulted with the Rubrick of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer; which is the unqueſtionable rule you ought to go by: of the Authority whereof if you do in the leaſt doubt, let me adviſe you (inſtead of going to the Biſhop to conſult about it) to go and conſult with the two Acts of Parliament for the Uniformity of publick Prayers, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments: and then conſider with your ſelf, whether any ſingle perſon's authority can diſpenſe with the obſervance of that, which is not onely confirm'd and ratifyed by the whole body of the Clergy, the Church repreſentative, but is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29585:4"/>incorporated into the Laws of the Land, and has the Supreme Power of the Nation for its Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment. But Oh! the invincible neceſſity of complying with the humours of the people! which is ſuch as no law can controll, or withſtand the force of: and therefore if <hi>Mahomet</hi> will not come to the mountain, the mountain muſt go to <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met;</hi> if the people will not ſubmit to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there's no help for it but, the Government muſt ſubmit to them.</p>
            <p>But you have ſomething farther yet to offer in your Vindication; which is, that you have often, both from the Desk, and the Pulpit, <hi>commended</hi> the practice of the Church; and anſwered the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Diſſenters againſt it: But had you not the Biſhop's Orders for that too? or did you doe it of your own accord? if you did, the Church is infinitely beholding to you for your <hi>commending</hi> the practice of thoſe things, which ſhe has poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively injoyn'd the performance of: as if a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory diſcourſe of yours in ſuch things, were more to be regarded, than the Churches Authority, in her poſitive injunctions of them. But to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend what the Church has commanded, is not all that you have done on her behalf; for you have likewiſe anſwered the Objections of the Diſſenters againſt her; and yet, ſuch obſtinate people are they, that they will not be anſwered by you; for you tell us, that, upon the preſent Vicar's requiring
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29585:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Orders of the Church to the duly obſerv'd, and your compliance with ſuch Orders, the Diſſenters (notwithſtanding you have ſo well anſwer'd their objections) will not be brought to comply with them; <hi>but either ſend for Non conformiſts to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize their children, or let them remain unbaptiz'd.</hi> But now, ſince you are ſo good at anſwering Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, I deſire you to anſwer one of mine: now the thing, which I Object againſt you, is your juſtifying your ſelf, in breaking the Orders of the Church, by your having the Biſhop's for it. For how does <hi>his</hi> Orders, for breaking <hi>thoſe</hi> of the Church, juſtifie you in the breach of them? does <hi>his</hi> being criminal make you ever the leſs guilty? how you have anſwer'd the Objections of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, I know not; ſure I am, that your own diſſent, in the particular you are charg'd with, cannot to God and your own Soul be anſwer'd by you; unleſs you repent of it: other means, to acquit your ſelf by, I know not of. But of this there appears nothing at all in your Reply; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther much the contrary: for there though you tell us of your ready compliance with the preſent Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car's Orders, who hath requir'd that the Orders of the Church be duly obſerv'd, (and God's peace, and the Churches be with him for it) yet I perceive ſomething, as well as you; which is, that you are ſtill hammering upon the ill conſequences, that will follow upon ſuch obſervance, and thereby plainly ſhew, that it is not the Orders of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29585:5"/>Church, but thoſe of the preſent Vicar you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to. So that had you but ſuch another Vicar to conſult with, as you had formerly; you wou'd certainly be at your old Non-conforming tricks again, (which I find you have a months mind for) and think a compliance with the humours of the people to be much more neceſſary, than obedience to the Orders and Conſtitutions of that Church, which (by trimming in it) you wou'd be thought to be a ſound member of. And thus you ſee, how well you have Vindicated your ſelf of the firſt crime charg'd againſt you; your chriſtning without Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: which, by your own confeſſion, you ſtand charg'd with, and have not as yet, by any thing you have ſaid, acquitted your ſelf of the guilt of.</p>
            <p>I come now to the other thing charg'd upon you; which is your chriſtning without the ſign of the Croſs: and here likewiſe you own the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact, but poſitively deny, that the Orders of the Church were broken by it. Now in aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, you aſſert a manifeſt falſhood; the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite whereto is a moſt plain and evident truth; which is, that the Orders of the Church were broken by you; and that more ways than one. For firſt, that which you make to be the cauſe of your omitting the ſign of the Croſs, (to wit, the gaining of a Proſelyte) is a thing not allow'd of by the Church, which permits the omiſſion of it, onely in the caſe of private Baptiſm, and then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29585:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>onely for expeditions ſake, as to the preſent uſe thereof. For if the child, who is after this ſort Baptiz'd do afterward live; ſhe requires that it be brought to Church; where, after the Congregation is certified of its being duly Baptiz'd, the Miniſter is to demand the Name of it, of the Sponſors; which being by them pronounc'd, he is to proceed to take their engagement for it; and then, ſaying the words preſcrib'd for the ſign of the Croſs, to ſign it with it. Now how well you obſerv'd the Orders of the Church in this particular, let any man judge; nay, be you your ſelf the judge of it. This is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the firſt manifeſt falſhood, in your aſſerting, that the Orders of the Church were not broken by you, in what you did, but this was not the onely thing, you broke the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church in. For in the 2d. place it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears plainly, by what you ſay, that your private Baptiſm was onely the publick Baptiſm admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred privately: otherwiſe what do you mean, by ſaying that the reaſon of your omitting the ſign of the Croſs was onely to gain a Proſelyte to the Church? when, in the caſe of private Baptiſm, the preſent uſe of the Croſs is no ways injoyn'd you by it: but then onely in caſe the child do live to be afterwards brought to Church; as has been abovemention'd. Which being moſt undoubtedly true; how ſhould the omiſſion of that, be a means to gain you a Proſelyte to the Church, the uſe whereof, in the preſent caſe, is no where injoyn'd you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29585:6"/>by it? 'Tis plain therefore that your private Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm was onely the publick Baptiſm adminiſtred privately. So that this is another particular, wherein the Orders of the Church were broken by you. And therefore, by your being ſo poſitive in aſſerting that they were not, you give your ſelf the lie; which a man, that will be ſo uncivil as to give himſelf, muſt take, and there is no help for it. But then, in the 3d. place, what a moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous courſe, did you take to gain a Proſelyte to the Church, by an action that bears a direct oppoſition to the Rules and Conſtitutions of it? here again your action gives you the lie, and flies directly in the face of you; and the honeſty of the one, is the beſt comment on the integrity of the other: that is, your breach of the Orders of the Church plainly tells us what Proſelytes you are for gaining into it; ſuch as, like your ſelf, are Non-conforming Conformiſts: who are ſome of the worſt Enemies the Church has; in that they herd themſelves in it, onely to lay it waſte, by breaking down the incloſures of it. Theſe are ſuch Proſelytes, as the Church had never greater reaſon, than now, to be afraid of; and therefore ought the Governours and Paſtours thereof, nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly to obſerve the motions of thoſe, who are the gainers of them.</p>
            <p>As for the other thing you are charg'd with, namely, your omitting to pray for the Duke of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29585:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>York;</hi> I muſt ſay this in abatement of your charge; that you are not in this particular (as you are in the other two) guilty by your own confeſſion. For here we have you poſitively denying the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact, and bringing ſome hundreds of your conſtant Auditors to atteſt the truth of what you ſay; of which I was none; and therefore cannot ſay one way or other, having never ſo much as heard of your name, before you had expos'd it in Print; and made it publick, to your own ſhame, and diſgrace. But though I am thus a perfect ſtranger to your perſon, yet having ſtudied men, as well as books, and endeavour'd to underſtand the one by the other; give me leave to tell you, that if the Proverb, <hi>Ex ungue leonem,</hi> be true; that is, if a man may know the Beaſt by his paw; I have ſeen enough under the hand of one Mr. <hi>Smy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies,</hi> Curate of <hi>Cripple-gate,</hi> to convince me that he is not a man of that temper he pretends himſelf to be; but may ſhrewdly be ſuſpected to be a Woolf, onely in Sheeps cloathing. And therefore, whether he omitted to pray for the Duke, or no, it matters not; who, queſtionleſs, had the bill of Excluſion gone forward, wou'd have more readily excluded him his prayers, than ever he put any perſon into them.</p>
            <p>As to your valuing your ſelf upon your being call'd Tory, in the days of Whiggiſm; let me tell you, that the very worſt of Trimmers now, wou'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29585:7"/>have paſs'd for ſuch in thoſe days: but there being ſince an alteration in the times, but none in you; you muſt remain, what you were then, a rank Trimmer ſtill. But you value not opprobrious names, you tell us, ſo long as you are faithfull and induſtrious in the diſcharge of your Office. Very induſtrious indeed in you have been in the diſcharge of it; even to the going beyond the bounds of your duty, and fetching a compaſs out of the Pale of the Church, to bring your Proſelytes into it. But now how faithfull you have been in the diſcharge hereof, let the foremention'd inſtance of the courſe you took to gain a Proſelyte, be a moſt pregnant and convincing proof. There is another thing, you tell us, is objected againſt you; and which, by means of ſome ſpitefull people, as you call them, came lately to the ear of his Majeſty, and that is your being an aſſociate with Diſſenters: now thoſe ſpitefull people, as you term them, wou'd from any man's mouth, but that of a ſpitefull Trimmer, have been termed Loyal. But how do you juſtifie your ſelf in this particular? why, by telling us, that in your being ſo, <hi>you are no greater a friend to Phanaticks, than our Great Maſter was to Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Sinners.</hi> But how does our Saviour's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with theſe, juſtify your converſing with Diſſenters? you muſt not reckon <hi>them</hi> amongſt <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans</hi> and <hi>Sinners;</hi> for if you do, as great a friend as you are to them, they will, I can aſſure you, be none to <hi>you.</hi> Our Saviour's example therefore,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29585:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the preſent caſe, ſtands you in no ſtead at all; it had been much more to your purpoſe to have found him converſing with the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees;</hi> who were righteous much after the ſame manner your Phanaticks are; in that they were Separatiſts (as their very name imports) upon the account of the good opinion they had of themſelves, and of their being better, and holier than other men. Now our Saviour (and by the Authority of whoſe example you think to juſtify your ſelf) was ſo far from aſſociating himſelf with thoſe, that he every where declines it; and, inſtead of treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them kindly at any time, denounces no leſs than eight ſeveral woes at once againſt them; for their Hypocriſie: and, at another time, tells them plainly, that he came not to call ſuch righteous perſons, as they were, but ſinners to repentance. So that you ſee, our Saviour's <hi>kindneſs</hi> to Publicans and ſinners will not juſtify <hi>yours</hi> to Republicans and Schiſmaticks. Theſe being thoſe diſorderly walkers the Apoſtle (2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6.) injoyns you to withdraw your ſelf from, which, however ſtrictly there injoyn'd you, is that you cannot well doe; leſt you ſhould want Compurgators for your Loyalty: neither are they willing, I believe, that you ſhould withdraw your ſelf; leſt <hi>they</hi> ſhould want <hi>one</hi> for themſelves: which is ſuch a kindneſs as you cannot in gratitude deny them. For, according to the Proverb of <hi>Scabunt ſe mutuo muli,</hi> one good turn, you know, requires another. But now, after
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29585:8"/>all this great love and kindneſs own'd betwixt you and the Phanaticks; how comes it to paſs, that you have the confidence to tell us, that the <hi>greateſt</hi> kindneſs, <hi>you ever did for any Diſſenters from the Church, was for a family of Papiſts; whoſe whole eſtate was unjuſtly kept from them, by a Proteſtant Diſſenter?</hi> Now what you did for theſe Papiſts, was nothing more than purely an act of juſtice: and is the doing any man common juſtice, ſuch a mighty act of kindneſs in your eſteem? it is ſo, it ſeems, when done to a Papiſt. And therefore leſt your party ſhould take this ill at your hands, and think you Popiſhly affected for it; you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently tell us, that you <hi>think you could as ſoon be a Jew, as a Popiſh Chriſtian.</hi> Now, was this well ſaid, or no, do you think? might you not have us'd a little ſofter expreſſion? and ſaid, that you cou'd as ſoon be a <hi>Turk,</hi> as a Popiſh Chriſtian? (for the Turks, you know, have ſome ſmall Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for our Saviour; whereas the Jew has none; but ſpits in his face, and treats him with ſcorn and contempt) And wou'd not your <hi>Tekelites</hi> have lik'd <hi>that</hi> expreſſion, altogether as well as the other; I am apt to believe they wou'd; however you muſt have a care of complying too far with the humours of the people; leſt ſuch complyance, as brought you once to omit the ſign of the Croſs, for bringing a Trimmer into the Church, bring you at laſt to omit the Croſs it ſelf, for bringing the Jew in thither.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:29585:8"/>
            <p> In your next Paragraph, you tell us, <hi>that you have ſuffer'd in your reputation, by being kind in the diſtribution of other mens Charity, (where you were not limited by the Donor) to all that were in exceſſive want, without reſpect had to the Opinion of any.</hi> But now, notwithſtanding this Profeſſion of yours, I much queſtion whether, if a Jew, or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Chriſtian had come in your way, you would not (unleſs limited by the Donor) have been kinder to the one, than to the other; or at leaſt made it croſs or pile, which ſhould have been reliev'd by you. And now, after all this, you are pleas'd to tell us, <hi>That you are content to ſuffer in your good name; ſince this hath been the lot of divers others, who are a thouſand times more deſerving than your ſelf.</hi> That there are divers in the Nation ten thouſand times more deſerving than your ſelf, is a matter that very well deſerves belief; as being a thing paſt all manner of doubt: but now, that ſuch as theſe, have ſuffer'd, in like manner, as you have done, is far enough from being alike credible: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, before it gain credit with me, I muſt have ſome farther proof of the truth thereof, than barely your ſaying of it. However, ſuppoſing it to be true; does their ſuffering the ſame with you, make your caſe one jot the better or theirs ever a whit the worſe? Our Saviour himſelf was in the very ſame condemnation with the two Thieves, that ſuffer'd with Him; and yet, I hope, you will not ſay, that He was ever the leſs Innocent, or they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29585:9"/>ever the leſs criminal? the application is eaſie and obvious; and therefore I leave you to make it. <hi>But ſome of the moſt eminent Divines of the Church of England have been falſly accus'd, you ſay;</hi> well, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing again this to be true; I ask you again, whether their being falſly accus'd, does make your accuſation ever the leſs true? If it does not, to what purpoſe is it mention'd by you? unleſs it be ſlily to inſinuate the truth of your own innocency, from the falſhood of their accuſation: but this is a cheat too groſs to paſs upon any man; for who wou'd think ever the better of a Malefactor, who, to ſalve his reputation at the Gallows, ſhou'd ſay, that it was many an honeſt man's fate to be hang'd, as well as his? the application here likewiſe is very eaſie; and therefore are you again left to make it. So that you ſee, 'tis not the hard rubbing your crimes, againſt other mens innocency, which will fetch off the guilt of them.</p>
            <p>As to the Magiſtrate you ſpeak of, on whom ſome think, as you tell us, that the <hi>Obſervator</hi> has been throwing his dirt, all, that I have to ſay, is this; that the <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s buſineſs is not to throw dirt upon any man, that does not deſerve to have it caſt on him: in whoſe farther Vindication (as to what I have ſeen of his papers) give me leave to tell you; that there is no dirt, that he hath thrown upon any man, but what will, in your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to wipe it off, ſtick cloſe upon your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29585:9"/>ſelf: there being not a perſon in the whole herd of the Faction, reflected on by him, whom he has not treated, with more civility, than he deſerves: and therefore when you tell us of <hi>ſome, whoſe Loyalty, and Conformity to the Laws of God, the King, and the Church, lye more in their talk, than in their practice:</hi> if, among thoſe ſome, you reckon the <hi>Obſervator</hi> for one; I muſt tell you plainly, that I heartily wiſh, and that for the ſake of all thoſe Laws you mention, that your Loyalty and Conformity to them, had lain half ſo much, either in your talk or practice, as his hath unqueſtionably done in both. Here therefore, inſtead of wiping off the dirt from your Magiſtrate, you are caſting it on the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> but 'twill not ſtick there. For he is a perſon of too untainted a reputation for his Loyalty, ever to have it Fly-blown by the breath of a ſtinking Trimmer.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, to anſwer thoſe few queſtions, which you ſedately propoſe to the <hi>Obſervator.</hi> The firſt whereof is, <hi>whether if mens calmly treating the Proteſtant Diſſenters, ſpeaks them Trimmers, his wonderfull mildneſs and gentleneſs towards Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Diſſenters does not make him juſtly liable to the charge of Trimming?</hi> to this I anſwer; that the charge of this wonderfull mildneſs and gentleneſs of his towards the Papiſts is a moſt malitious ſlander. However for the proof hereof, you inſtance in his endeavouring to ſham and ridicule the Popiſh Plot;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29585:10"/>and for making good the truth of this, you refer us to the <hi>Obſervator, Aug.</hi> 30. this <hi>Obſervator</hi> I have conſulted; and find it to be ſo far from ridiculing the Popiſh Plot, that it gives us a true ſtate and account thereof: and therefore if you had taken a quarter of that pains for leſſening the Phanatick Plot, which he has done for giving us a true ſtate of the Popiſh one; (which is by you malitiouſly call'd ſhamming of it) you had taken infinitely too much: there being that vaſt oddes between them; and ten thouſand times more proof for the one, than for the other. Hitherto therefore, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears no ſuch wonderfull kindneſs of the <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> towards the Papiſts. But what ſhall we ſay then of his being ready, on all Occaſions, to doe that juſtice to the Papiſts, as to acquit <hi>them</hi> of the Murther of the late King, by laying it on the Phanaticks? this ſure, though an act of pure ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, yet being done for the Papiſts, muſt, in your eſteem of it, paſs for a wonderfull act of kindneſs towards them. But what now? if he has been thus wonderfull kind to them, muſt he preſently, to purge himſelf of the ſuſpicion of Popery, or of being Popiſhly affected, declare, as you have done, that, notwithſtanding the juſtice he has done them, he cou'd as ſoon be a Jew, as a Popiſh Chriſtian? No, there's no need for it: he has taken a much better courſe for the clearing himſelf from being a Papiſt, having taken the Sacrament on it, that he is none. And therefore, though he ſhould own
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29585:10"/>a greater kindneſs for the Romiſh Church, than for the Jewiſh Synagogue, and own likewiſe a greater charity for thoſe, that pay too much reverence to the Croſs, than for thoſe, who treat it with ſcorn and contempt; yet will none, but a Trimmer of a Proteſtant, ever think him the more inclining to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or believe him to be a Trimmer for it. When therefore you demand of him, <hi>whether you may not ſpeak to him in his own dialect, and in moſt of his own words as followeth; why this is right Trimming,</hi> &amp;c. I anſwer, no; for thoſe words, as us'd by him to you, are moſt pertinent and proper; but as us'd by you to him, are plainly ridicul'd by you; and ſound no better out of your mouth, than thoſe words of the Apoſtle, of obeying God rather than man, do out of a Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick's; which words, when us'd by the Apoſtle, were moſt ſignificant; but out of the mouth of a Phanatick (who, under the pretext of Conſcience of obeying God, rather than man, obeys neither) are intolerable.</p>
            <p>Your 2d. demand of the <hi>Obſervator</hi> is, <hi>whether he did more fooliſhly, or ſpitefully, in asking, whether, by the Prince of this World, he meant the King of Great Britain, or the Prince of the Air?</hi> in anſwer to which, I demand of you, whether you did more fooliſhly, or Phanatically, to ſuggeſt, as you do, that the Laws of Chriſt, and the Laws of the Land, are at odds with one another? and that the putting the latter in execution againſt the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29585:11"/>is a cruelty inconſiſtent with the mildneſs and lenity of the former?</p>
            <p>Your 3d. demand of him is, <hi>whether his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing (as he often does) that men, who have once imbib'd Phanatick principles can never become ſincere Comformiſts, be not to ſuggeſt, either that the Arguments to Conformity are of little or no force, or that the Clergy are too weak to urge them?</hi> to which I anſwer, that it ſuggeſts neither: but the thing, it plainly ſuggeſts to us, is the incorrigible obſtinacy of the Faction; who have the ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Jew in them: and therefore as ſoon may we expect, that the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> ſhould change his skin, and the Leopard his ſpots, as a factious and thorough-pac'd Phanatick become a ſincere convert.</p>
            <p>As to your 4th. demand of him; wherein there are ſeveral impertinent Queres tack'd together, I anſwer, that, in his taking notice of Seditious and Phanatical diſcourſes from the Pulpit, he neither aſſumes to himſelf the Office of a Biſhop, nor charges <hi>them</hi> with the neglect of it: but, like a worthy Patriot, ſtrenuouſly maintains the Poſt he has undertaken; and makes good the character of a Loyal and Faithfull <hi>Obſervator:</hi> who having heretofore diligently obſerv'd every motion and ſtep, which the Faction made towards the late Rebellion, rais'd by them, is every way the fitteſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29585:11"/>perſon (as being the beſt able) to judge of the like ſteps and progreſs, they are now making and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on foot again, towards the raiſing of another. Such a Spie, as this, is exceeding uſefull in the Government, for Obſerving the motions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of ſuch, as, under a pretext of ſupporting, ſlily endeavour the Subverſion of it; and therefore may very well be allow'd, in ſome caſes, to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madvert on the Diſcourſes of the Pulpit; as for inſtance, in the Caſe of the Diſſenters Sayings, where he has meddled with the Diſcourſes of the Pulpit to ſome purpoſe: and what if, to theſe Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Pulpit, he ſhould, in the next Edition of them, add ſome of yours from it? might not all this now be done by him, and yet he neither go beyond the bounds of his own duty, or charge the Biſhops with the neglect of theirs? <hi>but all this is done, you ſay, upon no better evidence than the tales of Goſſipping Buſy-bodies, or malitious people;</hi> now, if the tale be true, what matter's it, who tells it; and what if ſome are as buſie in bringing their help to quench a popular flame, as others are to kindle it? and when the flame is begun, and the Faction has put the Government into a tottering condition; what if ſome are as ready to ſupport it, as others are to ſhake and undermine it? whilſt, under a pretence of bearing one anothers Burthens, they are putting themſelves into a readineſs of poſture for bearing away the Government it ſelf upon their ſhoulders. And indeed 'tis but ſaying to the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29585:12"/>Faction at any time, inſtead of the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> that the Papiſts are upon them; and, <hi>Sampſon</hi> like, they are ready to ariſe, and unhinge the Government, and to bear away with them the main ſupporters thereof; all fear and reverence towards their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, together with religion, property, liberty, laws and all.</p>
            <p>As to your fifth demand, I anſwer, that the <hi>Obſervator's</hi> reflecting on ſome Doctours of our Church, for dedicating Books to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> (that <hi>Tony</hi> of a Peer) caſt no unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly reflexion upon his Majeſty for making him his Lord Chancellor, when he did: but for you to make ſuch a queſtion, is, doubtleſs, ſawcily to intermeddle in affairs you underſtand not: for his Majeſty, who is a Wiſe and Underſtanding Prince, did, queſtionleſs, very well underſtand the temper of the man, at the time he conferr'd that High Honour on him. But what if his Majeſty thus rais'd him up, either to lay the greater obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to loyalty on him, or for the ſame cauſe that God did heretofore <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that his diſloyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his Prince might be the more conſpicuous by his fall? (as <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s that fell was) or for other reaſons of ſtate, and ends of Government beſt known to his Majeſty? muſt <hi>Titus Oates,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of his Fraternity immediately fall to making an Idol of this Chancellor, by worſhipping of him? when his Majeſty ſaw this, and that the people fell
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29585:12"/>a bowing to him, and he again to the people; and that they mutually worſhip'd one another; twas high time, His Majeſty thought, to break this Idol of a Chancellor in pieces, or rather, by throwing him down to the bottom of contempt, to make him burſt in ſunder with diſcontent. In relation to whom, all that I have to add farther, is heartily to wiſh that, ſince a double portion of his unquiet ſpirit ſtill reſts among the Faction, the curſe, which befell him, may likewiſe befall them; and that the envy, which the Faction have at the proſperity of His Majeſty's late good ſucceſs in his proceedings, may be the rottenneſs of their bones, as the like envy in him was the rottenneſs of his.</p>
            <p>As to your ſixth Quere, wherein you ask the <hi>Obſervator, Who that Trimmer was, who being ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially interrogated about ſomebodies receiving the Sacrament, and after ſeveral interrogatories, repli'd that it was ſitting, but very decently?</hi> I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to ſay, but onely to tell you, that ſince you boaſt of thoſe vaſt numbers, you have brought to the Sacrament, and of their exact Conformity to the Orders of the Church in their receiving of it; I deſire to know of you, whether to gain a Proſelyte to the Church, you never did in that particular break the Orders of it? that is, never adminiſter the Sacrament to any, that cou'd kneel, in any other poſture than that of kneeling? now if, by the Oath you have taken not to adminiſter it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29585:13"/>otherwiſe, you will tell me, that you are ready at any time to take the Sacrament on it, that you never did; you ſhall then be diſcharg'd from all ſuſpicion of being the above mention'd Trimmer: but till I know, that you are ready to purge your ſelf after this manner, you will ſhrewdly be ſuſpected, either to be that individual Trimmer, or at leaſt one of his Fraternity.</p>
            <p>In your laſt Quere to thc <hi>Obſervator,</hi> you ask him, <hi>whether it were not more adviſable, that, for the future, he ſhould ſuffer thoſe to live in quiet, who are no leſs loyal, but far more peaceable than himſelf?</hi> To which I anſwer, that this is nothing elſe, but to beg the queſtion; by taking it for granted, that he has not done, what you ſay is moſt adviſable: but let one ſingle inſtance be produc'd to the contrary; and I'll undertake for him for the future, that he ſhall take your advice. Wherefore, ſince you tell us, <hi>that no good man will ever think, that Rebels or Diſturbers of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be too ſeverely laſh'd by his pen;</hi> let me deſire you for the future, not to be ſo ſenſible of the ſmart, when you find them laſh'd by it. And thus I have anſwered the ſeveral queſtions, propos'd by you to the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> and might now therefore, take leave of your Reply to him; but that I there find ſome other little things objected againſt him; the firſt whereof, is his <hi>profanely</hi> entituling one of his Papers, <hi>An Edifying Diſcourſe concerning bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29585:13"/>one anothers Burthens;</hi> now, how come your diſcourſes to be ſo ſacred, that the <hi>Obſervator</hi> cannot uſe one of them for his Title-page without profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of it? Again, another objection againſt him, is, <hi>that his Papers are commonly read by a ſort of men, who take occaſion from them to revile and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure any whom they diſlike; and that thereby very innocent perſons greatly ſuffer in their reputation.</hi> Now ſuppoſing this true; are his Papers one jot the worſe, becauſe ſome men by miſapplying them, abuſe and make an ill uſe of them? no man ſure, will ſay they are: for then the Scriptures themſelves, the very beſt of Writings, may be impeach'd, as well as his; for theſe likewiſe are read by a ſort of men, who take occaſion from them to cenſure the worſhip of the beſt Eſtabliſhed Church in the whole World, and to revile and vilifie the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Government thereof: but now the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſurely are herein no ways blameable, nor is the ill uſe, that ſome men make of them, to be in any wife charg'd upon them, any more, than it is to be charg'd upon the wine, that ſome men are ſo wicked, as to debauch themſelves and others with it. So that you ſee, innocent perſons may be traduc'd by means of the <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s Papers, and yet the <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s Papers, be all that while very innocent of the abuſe of them. Again, you tell us farther, <hi>that there are ſome, who have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by his pen, who yet have been very kind to his purſe:</hi> but what is this, but to tell us, that the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29585:14"/>
               <hi>Obſervator</hi> is no Mercenary Scribler? none, that may be brib'd to write in favour of any man, who is not as hearty a lover of the King, and as true a Friend to the Government, as himſelf is: but as for all ſuch, as are ſo; let them be but once known to him, and whether they are kind to his purſe, or no, I'll undertake that he ſhall be ſo to them. Others again you tell us of, who, <hi>to your knowledge, have had a great honour for his Name and Family, and yet have been traduc'd by him:</hi> now here again, I muſt undertake for him, and tell you, that if there be any ſuch, as you ſpeak of, and who likewiſe have a juſt eſteem for him upon the account of his ſteady and unſhaken loyalty to his Prince, (which, to the immortal honour of his Name, ought never to be forgotten) and yet have ſuffered from his pen, or been traduc'd by it; he ſhall, not onely heartily beg their pardon for it, but ſhall for the future, court their friendſhip; and have the ſame honour and eſteem for <hi>them,</hi> which they have for <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, you having thus let fly at the <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator,</hi> and diſcharged your ſelf of all your rancour and malice againſt him, (but with no better ſucceſs than one that lets off a Gun, which by reaſon of the foulneſs thereof, recoiles upon himſelf) you tell us in the concluſion of your Reply, <hi>that you hope he will, e'er long, either be perſuaded, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to forbear his publications; ar at leaſt leave
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29585:14"/>Eccleſiaſtical matters and perſons to whom they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</hi> In anſwer to which, all that I have to ſay, is; that ſince he meddles with nothing either in Church or State, but what the intereſt of both obliges him to meddle with; none that wiſh well to either, will hope as you do; but rather believe that it were <hi>Sions</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> intereſt (for whoſe ſake you tell us you cannot be ſilent) that ſuch as you were put to ſilence. And whereas you tell us, that <hi>you doubt not but in a ſhort time, many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters will underſtand their errours and become lovers of the Church;</hi> give me leave to tell you, that I hope many in a much ſhorter time, will underſtand the Diſſenters themſelves, and be not onely <hi>true lovers</hi> of the Church and State, but of the <hi>Obſervator</hi> likewiſe for the ſake of both; whoſe intereſt he has all along ſo heartily embrac'd and maintained, and in the defence thereof has bravely ſtemm'd the torrent of a moſt violent and impetuous Faction, and ſtood the ſhock of a turbulent and rowling multitude; out-vying, as it were, hereby the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveableneſs of the rock it ſelf: in as much as the madneſs of the people (the rage whereof he has born the violence of) is more boyſterous and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, than is the Wind and Waves. Hereby like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, making up the character of <hi>Horace</hi>'s juſt and upright man; who ſtands ſo immoveably fix'd in his ſtation, as not to be thrown from it, although the Orbes themſelves crack and fly in pieces about his Ears.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29585:15"/>
            <p> And thus having done with your Reply, and vindicated the <hi>Obſervator</hi> from the malitious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny of it; I come now to make ſome brief reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on your <hi>Sermon</hi> annex'd to it; and here indeed to deal ingenuouſly with you (which is that which in your Preface to the Reader you deſire of him) 'tis not the plainneſs of it, which I diſlike in it; but that ſpirit of Phanaticiſm, which it ſavours of, and which runs through the whole of it. But the <hi>Sermon,</hi> you ſay, ſhall ſpeak for it ſelf; and ſo it does; and ſays juſt as much for it ſelf, as you do for yours: that is, it plainly tells us, to what party it belongs; and who they are it is deſign'd for the ſervice of. Whatever Diſcourſes therefore of this kind, you publiſh in your own Vindication, will to every impartial Reader, appear no other, than ſo many ſeveral Parts to the ſame Tune of Trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. Wherefore inſtead of making any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar animadverſions on your <hi>Sermon,</hi> I ſhall make this general one for all; that it is a piece calculated for the Meridian of the Faction of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex,</hi> but may without any ſenſible alteration, indifferently ſerve for any Conventicle of this Kingdom whatſoever: of the juſtice of which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion I leave every impartial Reader to judge; and you to think as you pleaſe of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
